Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We pick up on today's daf
דף daf is Daf Nun דף נ. Daf Nun. We pick up
four lines from the bottom on Mem-Tet Amud Bet מ"ט עמוד ב.
Mem-Tet Amud Bet. We just had a very important Gemara גמרא Gemara
about the basis of Lamed-Tet Melachot ל"ט מלאכות. Lamed-Tet Melachot.
Number one, how we get the number? Times it says Melacha מלאכה,
Melacha, Melechet מלאכת, Melechet, or a very interesting read from Rav Yoel
Bin-Nun I shared with you, the specific items that were made in
the Mishkan משכן Mishkan is how he reads the Gemara גמרא. Gemara.
But more importantly, the question of whether the source is the Mishkan
משכן, Mishkan, or is the Gemara גמרא Gemara even suggesting that the
Mishkan משכן Mishkan doesn't even serve as the source, which is radical
from everything we've been taught, but it is that is what the
Gemara גמרא Gemara sounds like as a possibility on the reading of
the Yereiot יריעות. Yereiot. So that was a very important Gemara גמרא,
Gemara, but now we get back to the direct discussions around what
you can insulate in. So the five lines, four lines from the
bottom, Gizei Tzemar גיזי צמר, Gizei Tzemar,
with wool shearings, Ve-ein Metaltelin ואין מטלטלין, Ve-ein Metaltelin, so you insulate
with those. Those don't add heat, they just preserve heat, but you
cannot move them. They're Muktze מוקצה. Muktze. Those are the types of
things that would go in your sewing box and therefore are considered
Muktze מוקצה Muktze on Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. So the question is going
to be how do you get your pot out of it? That
the Mishna משנה Mishna will continue with that discussion. But first let's
take a look at the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Amar Rava אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, Lo Shanu Ella She-lo Taman Bahem לא שנו אלא שלא
טמן בהם. Lo Shanu Ella She-lo Taman Bahem. They're only considered Muktze
מוקצה Muktze if you haven't used them to insulate Erev Shabbat ערב
שבת. Erev Shabbat. Aval Taman Bahem אבל טמן בהם, Aval Taman Bahem,
as soon as you've used them as insulator, Metaltelin Otam מטלטלין אותם,
Metaltelin Otam, they're no longer Muktze מוקצה Muktze because now you're using
them for a legitimate purpose and you've changed their identity and designation.
So we've seen some of this before, so this is like a
remember what the not yeah and right and remember we also saw
before a discussion about pieces of cloth that normally would be in
your sewing kit, but you use and anyway and the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says that unless you're really permanently changing their use, they remain
Muktze מוקצה. Muktze. So here Rava רבא Rava does not seem to
be taking that approach, but the Gemara's גמרא Gemara going to challenge
it. So Eitvei איתיבי, Eitvei, Ha-hu Me-Rabbanan Bar Yomei ההוא מרבנן בר
יומי Ha-hu Me-Rabbanan Bar Yomei to Rava רבא, Rava, so a one-day-old
rabbi asked Rava רבא, Rava, a one-day-old rabbinic student. The day he
entered into the Yeshiva ישיבה, Yeshiva, this is what was being discussed
and he had a Kasha קשיא Kasha on his first day at
the Yeshiva ישיבה. Yeshiva. What was his question? We have our Mishna
משנה, Mishna, Tomnin Be-Gizei Tzemar Ve-ein Metaltelin Otam טומנין בגיזי צמר ואין
מטלטלין אותם. Tomnin Be-Gizei Tzemar Ve-ein Metaltelin Otam. It says you can
insulate in wool shearings and you can't move them. Now you could
say that's unless you insulate with them, but then it goes on
and says Keitzad Hu Oseh כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad Hu Oseh, what
do you do if you did insulate with these wool shearings? Notel
Et Ha-Kisuy Ve-hen Noflot נוטל את הכיסוי והן נופלות, Notel Et Ha-Kisuy
Ve-hen Noflot, you lift up, right, you lift up the lid and
the things fall incidentally. It's a Mishna משנה Mishna is trying to
figure out how do you get the pot out given that the
insulator is Muktze מוקצה. Muktze. So clearly even once you've used it,
it still is Muktze מוקצה. Muktze. So how could Rava רבא Rava
say what he does? So what?
Can you put hot stuff in a thermos?
Is that considered Chatzmana הטמנה? Chatzmana? So that's a good question. So
Rav Moshe רב משה Rav Moshe has a Teshuvah תשובה Teshuvah about
that. From what I remember, he says no, but it's not a
problem. But anyway but meaning
yes, meaning yes you can do it. Okay, anyway Ella Im Hachi
Itmar אלא אם הכי אתמר. Ella Im Hachi Itmar. Okay, so here's
how Rava's רבא Rava's point must have been said. He couldn't have
just said across the board it's not a problem because the Mishna
משנה Mishna is clear that it does remain a problem. So here's
what Rava רבא Rava said. Amar Rava אמר רבא, Amar Rava, Lo
Shanu Ella She-lo Yichdam Le-hatzmana לא שנו אלא שלא יחדם להטמנה. Lo
Shanu Ella She-lo Yichdam Le-hatzmana. When is it that they remain Muktze
מוקצה? Muktze? If you did not re-designate them, you know, set them
aside for insulating. Aval Yichdam Le-hatzmana אבל יחדם להטמנה, Aval Yichdam Le-hatzmana,
if you said, "You know what? I'm no longer going to use
this stuff in my sewing kit. I'm going now, you know, use
it from here on in for insulator," then that will change their
identity. Then Metaltelin Otam מטלטלין אותם. Metaltelin Otam. Okay, it's relatively Pshita
פשיטא, Pshita, that is true. We'll see in a minute and this
is the question that was being asked the other days about what
do you need to change something's identity? How much just have it
in mind, how much to do something with it? So this may
be may be the what's not so Pshita פשיטא Pshita is what's
the degree of what's needed to change the identity. Anyway, that's one
version of Rava רבא. Rava. Itmar Nami איתמר נמי, Itmar Nami, it
was also said, Ki Ata Ravin כי אתא רבין, Ki Ata Ravin,
Amar Rabbi Yaakov אמר רבי יעקב, Amar Rabbi Yaakov, Amar Rabbi Assi
Ben Shaul אמר רבי אסי בן שאול, Amar Rabbi Assi Ben Shaul,
Amar Rabbi אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, so a chain of tradition going
back to Rabbi רבי. Rabbi. Lo Shanu Ella She-lo Yichdam Le-hatzmana לא
שנו אלא שלא יחדם להטמנה. Lo Shanu Ella She-lo Yichdam Le-hatzmana. All
of this is only if you haven't designated them for insulating. Aval
Yichdam Le-hatzmana אבל יחדם להטמנה, Aval Yichdam Le-hatzmana, if you designated them
for that, Metaltelin Otam מטלטלין אותם, Metaltelin Otam, then they stop being
Muktze מוקצה Muktze and you can move it. Ravina Amar רבינא אמר,
Ravina Amar, Ravina רבינא Ravina says, Be-shel Heftek Shanu בשל הפתק שנו.
Be-shel Heftek Shanu. We're talking about when is it that they don't
change their identity? When these are, you know, wool shearings that are
like like on a on a special shelf, meaning or from Rashi
רש"י Rashi it sounded a little bit if I was understanding Rashi
רש"י Rashi correctly that it was like on a on a ring
of like samples or some type of thing where clearly it has
been set aside for business use. Okay, so there's some the Geonim
גאונים Geonim say Heftek הפתק Heftek means like it's on a shelf
like on a, you know, in your in your in your store.
So it's clearly set aside for some type of a business use.
That's where that's where just using it once won't change its identity.
That's where you would need to re-designate. So that's the Mishna משנה
Mishna where the Mishna משנה Mishna says they remain Muktze מוקצה. Muktze.
But when Rava רבא Rava says that you when you use them
they stop being Muktze מוקצה, Muktze, that's things that might be until
now have been used for that but they're not clearly designated for
that purpose. So there their identity
changes. Use it once and you've changed its identity. It's not permanently
labeled that way, but something that really is like set aside in
this very clear way, it's in your drawer of samples, that type
of thing does not change its identity just because you happen to
use it once for insulator.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught so too: צמרי ליגיזי
צמר של הפקר, tzimri ligizei tzemer shel hefke, these wool things of
הפקר, hefke, again whatever they are, in your drawer set aside, your
samples, those remain מוקצה. Muktza. ואם התקינם בעל הבית להשתמש בהם, ve'im
hitkinam ba'al habayit lehishtamesh bahem, but if you fixed them, what does
that mean fixed them? Designated them, did something to them for the
purpose of using them, right, yeah, then מטלטלין אותן, metaltelin otan, then
you can. So what we are getting to is here, and this
is going to be nice because it'll get into this is going
to be the focus of the discussion today is changing something's identity
from מוקצה Muktza to not מוקצה. Muktza. How much do you have
to do? So until now we've held off actually two models, or
maybe implicitly three, and all of them are about to be revisited.
One is normal types of wool shearings that maybe
are מוקצה Muktza but they don't have a strong designation for some
other use, for this like off-limits use. That's easier to change its
identity. You just use it once as insulator changes its identity. So
there what changes its identity is a one-time use. Okay, maybe because
it was not as I said so much fully sort of pushed
away as completely. Another type of thing, הקדש, hekdesh, there what you
need to change its identity is
we have two languages. One is ייחדן, yichdan,
designate, which seems like something maybe verbal or in your mind but
not something physical. And the other התקינם hitkinam which seems to be
actually some physical thing of changing. So we have three possible ways
that you can change something that's מוקצה: Muktza: use it once,
designate it or have it in mind, and change it in some
way. Okay, and all those three we're about to revisit. So let's
take a look. Well, let's just take a look at this, I
want to get this on the table. So it says like this,
it says: תנא
רבה בר בר חנה קמיה דרב. Tana Rava bar bar Chana kamei
deRav. So רבה בר בר חנה Rava bar bar Chana taught in
front of רב. Rav. חריות של דקל, Charayot shel dekel, if you
have these beams from a palm tree, basically it's like a לולב
Lulav that's gotten hard and the leaves have fallen off. Okay, so
these are types of things that you would normally not use on
שבת, Shabbat, you might use for, you know, I don't know, for
some type of a building purposes or construction purpose. So now you
have these חריות של דקל charayot shel dekel שגדלן לעצים, shegedlan le'etzim,
or you just use it as firewood. So anyway you basically have
chopped them off the tree and your plan was originally to use
them as sticks, as wood for firewood or some type of as
I said construction purpose. ונמלך עליהן לישיבה, venimlach aleihen liyeshiva, and then
you decided, you know what, actually I'm going to use them to
sit on. Maybe I'll throw a lot down on the floor and
use them as an impromptu type of a floor covering. Okay, so
what do you have to do if you want to make them
not מוקצה Muktza for שבת? Shabbat? And all of this what you're
doing is before שבת Shabbat obviously. Once it's שבת, Shabbat, מוקצה Muktza
when שבת Shabbat begins, it remains מוקצה. Muktza. So what do you
have to do? צריך לקשר, tzarich lekasher, you have to take these
and weave them together as a mat. It's not enough to think
in your mind "I'm going to use it to sit on on
שבת". Shabbat Thinking isn't enough. You have to do something to change
its identity. Okay, that's doing something. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, says: אין צריך לקשר, ein tzarich lekasher, you
don't have to knot them together, presumably thinking about them is enough.
Okay. What? בין השמשות. Bein hashmashot. Right, this is before בין השמשות,
bein hashmashot, so that during בין השמשות bein hashmashot it already has
this new identity. Okay, not this has to be done before sunset
before שבת Shabbat enters. הוא תני לה והוא אמר לה, Hu tani
lah vehu amar lah, so רבה בר בר חנה Rava bar bar
Chana taught this ברייתא Braita and then he said the following comment:
הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Halacha keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel, we rule
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that you do
not have to actually physically change it, just having them in mind.
That's so two positions: physically change and having in mind. Now we're
going to see a third position. איתמר, Itamar, we have another statement
of this debate, or whatever, we have a statement similar to related
to this: רב אמר קושר, Rav amar kosher, רב Rav says if
you have these types of sticks that you want to use you
have to knot them together like you weave them to make them
into a mat.
רב
אמר קושר. Rav amar kosher. ושמואל אמר חישב, uShmuel amar chishav, and
שמואל Shmuel says you think. So those you just designate them even
in your mind, even a non-verbal designation. So those are the two
positions we saw before. But now here's a third position: ורב אסי
אמר יושב. veRav Assi amar yoshev. You don't have to think, you
don't have to tie them, just sit on them. Just use them
once in that function and that changes their identity. ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbat, ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. What?
No, because חישב chishav is... good question. I mean why would you
sit on it if you're not planning on sitting on it? But
doesn't mean you fell on it. No, but חישב chishav means like
you're designating it for "this is what I'm going to do with
it on שבת". Shabbat Maybe extreme would be like "I'm designating it
this is what I'm going to use it for forever", but at
least I'm designating this is what I'm going to use it for
on שבת. Shabbat. That's חישב, chishav, to redesignate it at least for
שבת. Shabbat. יושב Yoshev is: I had no particular plans for שבת,
Shabbat, I was just sitting on it ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, but
once I sat on it that changed its identity. Even though I
only sat on it once, even though I originally chopped them down
for wood and you know was still in my woodpile because on
ערב... Erev... Friday I decided to take a few and sit on
it, those pieces of wood have now changed their identity. Alright? So
that's what he says. So the גמרא Gemara says אף על פי
שלא קישר, af al pi shelo kishar, even if you did not
knot it, ואף על פי שלא חישב, ve'af al pi shelo chishev,
even if you did not think about reusing it.
By the way, and the חישב chishev רש"י Rashi says למחר. le'machar.
So רש"י Rashi says about planning what to do with it for
tomorrow. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא bishlama רב Rav
who דאמר d'amar כתנא קמא. ke'tanna kamma. So רב Rav says like
the first opinion in that ברייתא beraita with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, that when we have those posts you have
to knot them together. ושמואל נמי ve'Shmuel nami who דאמר d'amar כרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, ke'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, and שמואל Shmuel says like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that it's enough to
think about them, but at least you are designating them for the
next day. אלא רב אסי דאמר כמאן, ella Rav Assi d'amar k'man,
רב אסי Rav Assi says you didn't do anything physical, you didn't
designate them for the next day, you just used them on Friday
for that purpose, who's that going like? הוא דאמר כהאי תנא, hu
d'amar ke'hai tanna, oh we have a third תנא tanna that says
that. דתניא, de'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, beraita, יוצאין בפקורין ובציפא,
yotzin be'pakkurin u've'tzipa, you can go with פקורין pakkurin and ציפא. tzipa.
What are these things? So רש"י Rashi says they're types of bandages
that you would put on a wound. Now actually this raises interesting
questions. We're coming up to two פרקים perakim that's all about carrying.
For us we often tend to forget about these issues because we
have an עירוב. eruv. But a simple bandage on a wound might
be considered carrying if you don't have an עירוב eruv because it's
something that's seen as external, that it's there for healing purposes and
it's not actually a form of clothing. The things you're allowed to
have on you, it's not enough that they're being like on your
body, they have to be defined as clothing or jewelry in order
to not be considered wearing. So רש"י, Rashi, so if however what
it's doing is it's protecting the wound from, if it's got like
a sav on it and it's there to keep the sav on
the wound, then it's not really functioning like clothing. But if it's
there to protect the wound from being rubbed up against by your
outer garment, or let's say it's there to protect it from exposure
to the elements, then that it could do both, right? But if
that's part of its function then that actually is a function of
clothing. Right? I wear an undershirt so that my outer shirt doesn't
rub up against me. I wear a shirt so that maybe I'm
not exposed to the elements. So if it's doing a clothing-like function
it's okay, but if all it's doing is like applying a sav,
then that would be a problem. So that's how רש"י Rashi understands
this case. So you'd be concerned that this is just seen as
a type of a, they have something called not a bandage, what's
it called, something that's there for like having a sav on something?
A poultice? What's a poultice?
It's more like like
mushed-up herbs that are mixed with some kind of vinegar, oil.
Aha, but then you wrap but then you put something to keep
it on and the thing the purpose of that thing is just
to keep that mixture on, right? Not to actually protect the wound
itself. Right.
The poultice is on top of the wound.
Right, right. So that, so anyway so that's the issue. How do
you define this identity and that's going to be a question for
carrying. So according to רש"י Rashi we're making an analogy, what changes
something's identity in terms of the carrying question is also the type
of act you need to change its identity for the מוקצה muktzeh
question. Okay. So that or also can you move it? Is it
considered to be a proper clothing? Is it a type of a
מוקצה muktzeh issue? So that's how רש"י Rashi understands what these things
are. תוספות Tosafot has a very different explanation. Look at
תוספות, Tosafot, בפקורין ובציפא. be'pakkurin u've'tzipa. פירוש רש"י perush Rashi says, כיפה
שיש בה שיער, kippa she'yesh ba sei'ar, it's a type of a
skullcap that has hair sewn into it, it's a toupee or a
wig, ונותנו בראש הקרח, ve'notno be'rosh ha'kere'ach, and you put it on
the top of a bald person, ונראה ששיערו הוא. ve'nir'eh she'sei'aro hu.
Right, so it's like a toupee. Okay, so actually it's interesting because
the גמרא Gemara sometimes talks about a woman's wig and calls it
a פאה נוכרית, pea nochrit, but this is actually for תוספות Tosafot
this is more like a toupee maybe for men, yes.
Steinzaltz says that תוספות Tosafot got that from רב האי גאון. Rav
Hai Gaon.
תוספות Tosafot says he's got it from רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, but
maybe רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel got it from רב האי גאון. Rav
Hai Gaon.
Okay, and backwards in time.
There you go. Anyway, good question.
Let's finish this and then we'll get back to you. So it
says like this. So, דתניא, de'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, beraita,
יוצאין בפקורין ובציפא, yotzin be'pakkurin u've'tzipa, you can go out with these
things, בזמן שצבען בשמן וקשרן במשיחה. bizman she'tzva'an be'shemen u'kshar'an be'meshicha. So
when
you have, literally it means like dyed them with oil, which is
a funny phrase, but again for רש"י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafot it's more
about dyeing them because it's using the hair. To רש"י Rashi it's
more about you sort of put oil on them. And you have
wrapped them with a and you've wrapped them with some type of
a string. Somehow when you do that, I don't exactly understand how
רש"י Rashi is understanding the exact מציאות metzius here, the exact situation,
but רש"י Rashi says that shows that it's not being done for
רפואה refua purposes, it's somehow done there to protect your clothing. Maybe
if it's got the oil it creates some type of a seal
and a protection on you and it's not just there to keep
the to keep the sav on, it's actually there to do to
be there some type of a protection for the body. And that
makes them clothing. תוספות Tosafot would say that makes it more obvious
that it's actually like functional. as a wig at this stage. לא
צבען בשמן ולא כרכן במשיחה, Lo tzavan b'shemen v'lo karchan b'meshicha, if
he did not do those things, אין יוצאין בהם, ein yotzin bahem,
you cannot wear them because again, it's either it's only to keep
the, it's not a full garment or for תוספות Tosafot it's not
a full wig, ואם יצא בהם שעה אחת מבעוד יום, v'im yatza
bahem sha'ah achat mib'od yom, but if even if you didn't do
all of these things that are normally done, if you actually wore
it the day before in this stage, then מותר לצאת בהם, mutar
latzet bahem, then you can go out. So the point being by
even though this is talking about carrying by analogy, once you've used
something once, it's enough to change its identity and therefore we're making
the same point here. So what we have is three possibilities of
how you make something מוקצה muktzeh non-מוקצה. muktzeh. One is just planning
on it, thinking about it, to use it in a particular way.
The other is actually making a physical change. And the third is
just using it once. The using it once seems to be that
it's the most lenient. Certainly
the other two would suffice. But even if I just use it
once even with no plans about tomorrow, that's enough. And the one
that says you have to designate it seems like it's enough to
designate it for tomorrow. I should point out by the way that
the case that we started with with the insulation,
it was not enough to designate it for tomorrow when you insulated
it, you were clearly going to use this for the entire שבת,
Shabbat, right? Remember you insulated your pot with it. And nevertheless, at
least we said by some of those, maybe the ones that are
specifically samples or whatever, that that would not be enough to change
their identity. You would have to actually fully redesignate it or something
else. But in general we assume here that the designation for שבת
Shabbat suffices. Yes. Two questions.
One is I thought דברים שבלב dvarim she'b'lev are not דברים, dvarim,
at least we see that elsewhere. And
the second question is you know I found this whole wig thing
interesting you know from what the little chatter that I heard about
this aren't there also like בגד איש beged ish versus אשה isha
problems and you know toupees and whatnot? Yeah, are there or you
know?
Well okay, so just a quick answer by both. First of all
דברים שבלב אינם דברים dvarim she'b'lev einam dvarim is said almost exclusively
by sort of civil issues and interpersonal issues. I cannot be held
responsible or our contract cannot be shaped or our sale cannot be
shaped by what's in your head. I don't you know what's in
your head is in your head, that cannot be relevant to what
we're doing between the two of us. Okay, but what's between you
and God, okay, that you know that מחשבה machshava plays a big
role in terms of various areas of הלכה. halakha. So it's a
good question but it's very important to make that very clear distinction.
It's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot issue, exactly. In terms of you
know בגד איש, beged ish, those types of things change over time,
number one, you know the גמרא Gemara thought that actually a man
like a you know a looking in a mirror in order to
make sure his hair is straight or whatever, that could be a
בגד אשה beged isha because only women look in mirrors, men don't
look in mirrors. And it's funny because it's not even about clothing,
it's about appearance but it's not about clothing. Anyway,
so תוספות Tosafot at least for people that were actually you know
bald, you know maybe if a man didn't like maybe at the
time of the גמרא Gemara if a man didn't like his hair
and wanted to wear nicer hair, maybe that would have been considered
בגד אשה, beged isha, but you know for people that were bald,
you know so it's different, it's not absolute, it really depends on
what the norms of the society are. Yes.
Men wore wigs in colonial America. Right.
There you go. I mean whatever the norms of society are. The
גמרא Gemara thought that dyeing hair could have been a בגד beged
you know בגד אשה beged isha problem you know for men. Certainly
isn't because you dyed this. Yeah, but again this is for yeah
but that's creating a wig and this is for somebody who's bald
anyway it's a good point but the point is that these things
are not absolute they go by societal norms.
Is it considered like clothing essentially? Yeah. Does it have to be
clothing or jewelry in order to wear it out?
Yeah. Yeah exactly. Yes that's good point too it is becomes like
clothing it maybe becomes like a like a תכשיט tachshit um you
know but that also raises possibility of a third category as things
that become integrated into your body you know and תוספות Tosafot has
a whole
thing about about like what do they call
it crutches and so on so we will see plenty of that
in the upcoming פרקים. prakim. Yes. What about if you wear this
thing all the time? Right, so we'll see a lot about that
in the upcoming that makes it a lot better. So we'll see
about that in the upcoming פרקים prakim about that. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay.
אמר רב אשי אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Rav Ashi anan nami tanina,
we taught similarly in a ברייתא, baraita, התבן שעל גבי המיטה, ha'taven
she'al gabei hamita, if you have straw on a bed which is
we're assuming מוקצה muktzeh you may so לא ינענעו בידו, lo yenaneney
biyado, you cannot move it with your hand. You're using just straw
on a bed as a type of a mattress, but don't move
it with your hand because it's מוקצה muktzeh on שבת. Shabbat. אבל
מנענעה בגופו, Aval menaneha begufo, you can lie on it and move
around with your body because that's considered טלטול מן הצד tiltul min
hatzad or טלטול בגופו, tiltul begufo, which is permissible even with מוקצה
muktzeh when you're moving it with other parts of your body. אבל
אם היה מאכל בהמה, Aval im haya ma'achal behema, if it was
actual animal food, you're allowed to feed your animals so animal food
isn't מוקצה. muktzeh. Animal food animal food is on the straw? No,
no, the straw itself was planned to be used as animal food.
או שהיה עליו, O she'haya alav, well it depends if you have
the גרסה girsa עליו, alav, but it seems that the גרסה girsa
should be just straight מאכל בהמה, ma'achal behema, it was animal food.
או שהיה עליו כר או סדין מבעוד יום, O she'haya alav kar
o sadin mib'od yom, or you had on it some type of
like pillow or blanket from the day before, in that case then
clearly from yesterday you've already designated it as your mattress. It's not
just a chance happened to be on your bed and you want
to use it. You put the straw and then you put on
a pillow and you put on and a blanket, clearly you've designated
this as your mattress. In that case, so מנענעו בידו, menan'o beyado,
it's no longer מוקצה, muktzeh, you can move it with your hand.
שמע מינה, Shma mina, so you see that's good using it once
suffices. So here you didn't even use it, you didn't even lie
on it, but you did something the day before to show that
this was a use you were going to have for it. And
again the reason this is a חידוש, chiddush, you might think that
this is a higher standard you have to physically do something, but
the חידוש chiddush is that you don't have to be planning on
doing that tomorrow. The fact that you were doing it once on
Friday is enough even without actually designating it for all of שבת,
Shabbat, that's enough to change the status. Okay, and it seems like
from all of the from all of the things we've been reading
and we will continue to read, it seems like that the גמרא
Gemara is siding with this most lenient things that at least in
most cases just using once and certainly designated and certainly changing all
will be enough to change its status. So but תוספות Tosafot has
a question of exactly who we rule like. Anyway now the גמרא
Gemara goes on and says like this, ומאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Uman tanna dephalig alei d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, so
we've identified by name רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
who says designating, we've the we've identified the ברייתא braita at least
that speaks about using once, the whole ברייתא braita by the way.
Who is the who is the first opinion that says you have
to actually make a physical change in order to change its identity?
We know it's רב Rav who says it as an אמורא, Amora,
but who's the תנא? tanna? רבי חנינא בן עקיבא. Rabbi Chanina ben
Akiva. It's רבי חנינא בן עקיבא. Rabbi Chanina ben Akiva. דכי אתא
רב דימי אמר זהירי אמר רבי חנינא, Dekhi ata Rav Dimi amar
Zeiri amar Rabbi Chanina, פעם אחת הלך רבי חנינא בן עקיבא, pa'am
achat halach Rabbi Chanina ben Akiva, so we when they came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they told the story that once רבי חנינא
בן עקיבא Rabbi Chanina ben Akiva went למקום אחד lemakom echad to
a certain place ומצא חריות של דקל, umatza chariyot shel dekel, exactly
our case about which we started with which is these rods from
the palm tree, these sticks from the palm tree, שגדומו לשם עצים
shegadumu leshem etzim that they were cut off the tree initially to
be used as wood. ואמר להם לתלמידיו, v'amar lahem l'talmidav, and he
said to his students that it was ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, צאו
וחשבו כדי שנשב עליהם למחר. Tze'u v'chishvu k'dei sheneshev aleihem lemachar. Go
designate them, think about them, I don't know if you have why
you have to go think about them, let him think about them!
I really don't know. Maybe you have to be like looking at
all of them together to have all of them in mind anyway.
Like people that carry in the עירוב eruv but they'll ask someone
else. Yeah but this was I mean you're right but that's not
exactly but yeah. Anyway so he said go think about them כדי
שנשב עליהם למחר. k'dei sheneshev aleihem lemachar. Go go see what they
are maybe identify which ones you were planning which ones you weren't
planning and go think about them and plan to use them tomorrow.
Now that seems to be not our point, that seems I mean
that seems to be the more lenient opinion that designating is enough,
having them in mind. Where do you see the idea that you
have to physically do something? So because of the because of the
coda to this which is what? ולא ידנא, V'lo yadna, and then
the report says ended by saying I don't know אי בי משתה
הוה אי בי אבל הוה. i bei mishteh hava i bei avel
hava. That that was a special case and there was and it
was only allowed because I don't remember if it was exactly they
were going to a funeral or if it was some type of
a wedding party but there was some reason that they didn't have
time to do what they really needed to do. Okay so it's
only the postscript that
tells you really in general you need to do more, in
this type of a case that they were very busy ערב שבת
Erev Shabbat with a funeral or wedding they didn't have the chance
to go and to weave it and to make it, it was
enough to have it in mind. Now that's very interesting because normally
you would think like it's not a question of being strict or
lenient or whatever, if you've got a standard that something only changes
its identity when you physically change it, who cares if you didn't
have the time? But that wasn't enough to change its identity, I
feel very bad for you, but it wasn't enough to change the
identity. So it seems like and the גמרא Gemara is actually going
to say this that maybe it's you know it's a relative standard
meaning if you could be doing something to change it and you
did not go that far, normally if you want to make a
mat you would weave it together. If you didn't bother to weave
it together that shows you really weren't planning on using it for
a mat. Okay so what the problem of thinking is not that
thinking per se is a problem, the problem of thinking is not
that thinking it per se is not enough, it's not enough when
there is another opportunity available when you could do something better. So
when you can't do something better then thinking about it will be
enough and that's actually what the גמרא Gemara is going to move
into, there are cases where it's not meaningful to do a physical
change. So if it's not meaningful to do a physical change or
it's not a reasonable possibility then thinking about it would suffice though
no physical... you were going to say something? Okay very good. So
okay. So that's the base for מוקצה. muktzeh. You can't say it's
like an to make it a garment yeah yeah this is מוקצה.
muktzeh. Okay so that we see that on the one hand he
demands it but on the other hand it's somewhat only because it's
a possibility that he demands it. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, says like this, דווקא בי אבל ובי משתה, davka
bei avel ubei mishteh, so it's only because it
was a special
case like a funeral or a party דטרידי detridi that they were
distracted and they were too busy אבל הכא aval hacha but in
a normal case קשר אין לא קשר לא kesher in lo kesher
lo only if you tie it together, not if you don't. אמר
רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, מכניס אדם מלא קופתו, machnis adam m'lo
kupato, now we're going to have a perfect application of this about
when when the... A physical change is not a reasonable possibility. So
מכניס אדם מלא קופתו עפר machnis adam melo kuppato afar you can
bring in a full box of dirt on ערב שבת erev Shabbat
ועושה בו כל צרכו veoseh bo kol tzarcho and use
it throughout Shabbat because there are plenty of good uses of
dirt if you
have a dirt floor, right? You've got some stuff on
the floor, you want to throw some dirt on it, you've got
some poop somewhere, you've got to throw some dirt but dirt, you
know, so normally dirt is מוקצה. muktza. But if you brought a
box of dirt into your house, now it's all-purpose dirt and now
you can go ahead and use it and it's not מוקצה. muktza.
So it's a sandbox. Okay, so דרש מר זוטרא darash Mar Zutra
now מר זוטרא משמיה דמר זוטרא רבה Mar Zutra mishmei deMar Zutra
Rabba the elder said, והוא שיחד לו קרן זוית. vehu sheyichad lo
keren zavit. That's only if you designated a specific corner for it.
Now what's the reason for this? Well רש"י Rashi sounds like, you
know, it says it's a full box worth but רש"י Rashi sounds
like you actually dump the dirt out on the floor. So if
you didn't designate a particular space, then maybe the dirt just becomes
part of your dirt floor. What keeps it as seen as dirt
I'm going to use might mean that it has that you've designated,
you've put it in a corner. So you could have left it
in the box, right? The way רש"י Rashi is explaining it, you
could have left it in the box. Okay. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב
פפא Amru rabanan kumei deRav Pappa so the rabbis, meaning the rabbinic
students, said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, כמאן רבן שמעון בן גמליאל?
keman Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? That's according to Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
that designating is enough? דאי כרבנן de'ei kerabanan if it's the rabbis
that say you have to do something physical, הא אמרי בעינן מעשה
ha amri beinan ma'aseh they say you need some physical change in
order to re-change its status. אמר להו רב פפא Amar lehu Rav
Pappa רב פפא Rav Pappa said, אפילו תימא רבנן afilu teima rabanan
no, even the rabbis would agree in this case. Why? עד כאן
לא קאמרי רבנן דבעינן מעשה ad kan lo ka'amri rabanan debeinan ma'aseh
here it's said very explicitly, when do you need to make some
physical change? אלא מידי דבר עבידא במעשה ela midi debar avida bema'aseh
something where a physical change could be made and therefore it is
a meaningful thing to do and to do any less than that
would not be a sufficient designation. אבל מידי דלאו בר עבידא במעשה
aval midi delav bar avida bema'aseh what physical change are you going
to do to your dirt to make it more usable? Okay, so
something that there's no need for any act to be done, לא,
lo, then you don't need to do an act. An act is
only needed when that is what it will make it fully fit
and that's feasible, like we saw in the case of the wedding
party. So the גמרא Gemara says נימא כתנאי, neima ketannai, let's say
that is like a debate of תנאים. tannaim. בכל חפין את הכלים
bechol chapin et hakelim you can sort of like clean your vessels
with anything, rub them with anything to clean them, חוץ מכלי כסף
בגרתקון. chutz michli chesef begartikon. The one thing you cannot do is
you cannot scrub your silver vessels with גרתקון gartikon which is some
very type of abrasive thing because somehow רש"י Rashi says, I'll read
you the רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, כמו עפר שגדל בכלי כסף
וקורין לו אלם והוא עיקר תיקון כלי כסף וגורר טוח של כסף
רך הוא וממרק שהוא אב מלאכה. kemo afar shegadal bichli chesef vekorin
lo alum vehu ikar tikkun kli chesef vegorar tuach shel chesef rach
hu umemarek shehu av melacha. So רש"י Rashi says that this type
of thing not just removes the dirt, it actually smoothes the metal.
And to rub something and to smooth the surface is a מלאכה
melacha of ממרק. memarek. So therefore you cannot use it with this
type of a thing that actually not just removes the dirt but
creates this smoothing and is a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, what does that prove? So so far nothing, but the גמרא
Gemara says הנתר וחול מותר. hanetar vechol mutar. So that suggests that
using sand and נתר netar which is another type of a cleanser
they have, I don't know what does Steinzaltz say נתר netar is?
Natron. Natron. Washing soda. Okay, so these types of things are allowed.
Okay, והתניא vehatanya but didn't we see in a ברייתא braita נתר
וחול אסור netar vechol assur you cannot use sand and נתר netar
to clean your vessels. So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי mai lav beha
kamiflegi must it be that this is what they're debating? Now you
would think they're debating whether these are considered too abrasive and whether
they smooth the vessel too much, but the גמרא Gemara says no,
must be if we're talking about sand what they're debating is whether
it's מוקצה muktza or not, which seems very strange. It doesn't seem
like this is a מוקצה muktza discussion. Okay, but that's what the
גמרא Gemara suggests. Here's it, that this is what they debate: דמר
סבר בעינן מעשה demar savar beinan ma'aseh one master holds you can't
use sand because you need to do an act to it and
there's no way to transform sand, ומר סבר לא בעינן מעשה umar
savar lo beinan ma'aseh and the other master holds you don't need
to do an act and therefore you can use sand. So they're
debating a מוקצה muktza issue. גמרא Gemara says לא lo no, that's
not what's going on. דכולי עלמא לא בעינן מעשה dechulei alma lo
beinan ma'aseh everybody would say at least in this case where an
act isn't meaningful, you don't need an act to make sand not
מוקצה, muktza, to designate it is enough. ולא קשיא velo kashya and
it's not difficult anyway, here's what they're debating: הא רבי יהודה והא
רבי שמעון. ha Rabbi Yehuda veha Rabbi Shimon.
הא רבי יהודה דאמר דבר שאינו
מתכוין אסור והא רבי שמעון דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר.
ha Rabbi Yehuda de'amar davar she'eino mitkavein
assur
veha Rabbi Shimon de'amar davar she'eino mitkavein muttar. If you use this
גרתקון, gartikon, this אלם alum or whatever, it would definitely smooth. So
everybody says you can't do it, it would definitely smooth the silver.
The debate is these other types of cleansers where it might smooth
the silver and it might not. Can you use something that maybe
will smooth the silver? So that's your classic debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says don't do it because it might smooth, דבר שאינו מתכוין davar
she'eino mitkavein is אסור, assur, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says go
ahead and do it since it won't necessarily happen and you're not
intending it, it's not a problem. It has nothing to do with
מוקצה muktza and sand. So now the גמרא Gemara has to wrap
this up before we get back to our מוקצה muktza discussions. כמאן
אוקימתא להא דשרי Keman okimta leha deshary who are you saying it's
going like that? Who are you saying it's going like that it's
permissible? כרבי שמעון, KeRabbi Shimon, like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אימא סיפא,
Eima seifa, but look at the end of this of this ברייתא
braita that says that you can use the ברייתא braita that says
that you can use sand. What does the end of it say?
אבל לא יחופ בהם שערו, Aval lo yachof bahem sa'aro, you cannot
use it to wash your hair on שבת, Shabbat, to scrub your
hair on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, why? Because we're afraid that it'll make
the hair fall out. Okay, this is a very abrasive, it'll make
the hair fall out and you're not allowed to pull your hair
out on שבת. Shabbat. Now, what's about pulling your hair on שבת?
Shabbat? I was waiting for you to ask that. So, it could
be גוזז, gozez, but the problem with גוזז, gozez, like shearing your
sheep, is only when you want to use what you're shearing. So
it could be a type of תיקון הגוף tikun haguf because you
are actually, like you know, making your body look better. What? No,
well that's assuming that you did want to, you know, like it
was a stray hair or something. Anyway, anyway, let's bracket that. It's
a very good question. The גמרא Gemara will come up in a
later discussion about a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa
later, but Michael is always correct to be focusing on that. Maybe
it's only a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, whatever it is, but either way we
don't want you to be doing something that makes your hair fall
out on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, you're right. It's an important question, can,
is it really a דאורייתא d'oraita or not, what exactly is the
מלאכה, melacha, but we don't want you to do it. So therefore
don't use these types of cleansers on your hair because presumably that'll
definitely make your hair fall out. That's what we think if it's
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that would only be the problem if it
would definitely happen. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. ואי רבי
שמעון מי שרי? Ve-i Rabbi Shimon mi shari? But I can prove
to you that this רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say these things
don't necessarily make your hair fall out and they would be permissible.
Where do I know that from? דתנן, Detnan, from a not-case of
שבת, Shabbat, but from another case where it's more obvious you can't
pull out your hair, which is a נזיר. nazir. So there you
know why you can't pull out your hair if you're a נזיר,
nazir, you can't cut his hair. So what do we say? How
can a נזיר nazir wash his hair? What type of soaps and
can he use? Is he afraid that that'll make the hair fall
out? So it says נזיר חופף, Nazir chofef, a נזיר nazir can
scrub his hair, which is assumed to mean with these with sand
and with these types of cleansers, ומפספס, u-mefasfes, and you can like
rub his hair through his fingers through his hairs, אבל לא סורק,
aval lo sorek, he can't comb his hair with like a fine
comb because that will definitely pull out the hair. So there you
see that that we assume that this type of cleanser will not
definitely make the hair fall out. So if that's true, why does
this ברייתא braita have a problem with, you know, with doing it
on your hair and not using this sand on your hair and
not have a problem with using it on the silver vessel, if
it'll definitely, if we've seen that it won't definitely make the hair
fall out? So what's going on here? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אלא הא והא רבי יהודה, Ela ha ve-ha Rabbi Yehuda,
fine, they're both רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ותרי תנאי אליבא דרבי יהודה,
Ve-trei tanna'ei aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda, it's two תנאים tanna'im according to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. האי תנא אליבא דרבי יהודה סבר גריר, Hai tanna
aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda savar garir, one says that this sand will definitely,
I'm sorry, this sand has the potential of softening the silver, והאי
תנא אליבא דרבי יהודה סבר לא גריר, ve-hai tanna aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda
savar lo garir, it doesn't even have that possibility. Meaning, so what
do we have? We've got two ברייתות, braitot, right? They say don't
use alum on your silver but you can use sand. One says
you can use sand, one says you can't use sand. Okay, but
even the one that says you can use the sand says don't
use it on your hair. Now we know on the hair it's
only a possibility the hair will fall out. So if you're saying
don't use it on your hair, it has to be רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that doesn't like אינו מתכוין. eino mitkaven. So why does
he say you can use it on your silver? So he says,
ah, because maybe on the silver it definitely won't. Meaning there's three
possibilities: definitely will, which is even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees to;
maybe will, maybe won't, which is their debate; and obviously if it
definitely won't happen, or you know, extremely unlikely or whatever, then even
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's not a problem. So everybody says,
so don't use it on your hair, it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
it's a possibility. Don't use alum on the silver, that's a possibility.
Don't use the sand on your hair, that's a possibility. Can you
use the sand on your silver? So there the two ברייתות braitot
disagree. One says it's a possibility it'll soften it, don't use it,
and the other says it's not a possibility it'll soften it, go
ahead and do use it. Okay? So now we've got all the
various opinions about using this sand as a cleanser. Has nothing to
do with מוקצה, muktzeh, it's all according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
and the whole issue is whether it will definitely, whether it will
possibly cause a problem on your hair and on the silver and
then don't use it, or whether it will definitely not cause a
problem, at least on your hair, and then it will be okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes, continues. במאי אוקימתא כרבי יהודה? Bemai
okimta ke-Rabbi Yehuda? So you're saying this is רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end where it says
don't use it on your hair. It says אבל פניו ידיו ורגליו
מותר, aval panav yadav ve-raglav muttar, that you can use it on
your face and hands and feet. So that's a problem, I don't
get why that's allowed. If you can't use it on your hair,
why can you use it on your face, hands and feet? המעבירן
שערו, Hame'aviran she'aro, it causes the hair to fall out. What hair?
It assumes that you've got a beard. Okay? So if you've got
a beard, I don't understand. Why can't if you say אינו מתכוין
eino mitkaven is אסור, assur, as long as there's some possibility it
should be a problem, so if it's a problem... on the hair
on your head, it could be a problem on the hair on
your face. Says the גמרא Gemara says אי בעית אימא, ee bayis
ayima, wait, what's everybody saying? No, it doesn't have to be definitely
will. If it's רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, as long as there's a
possibility it'll make hair fall out. Doesn't matter more likely. Unless you
could say it like almost definitely not happen. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
once there's a reasonable chance, so let's take a look at what
the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אי בעית אימא, ee bayis ayima, if
you want I'll tell you, בקטן, bekatan, we mean that it's a
minor who doesn't yet have facial hair. ואי בעית אימא, ve'ee bayis
ayima, באישה, be'isha, or it's a woman. ואי בעית אימא, ve'ee bayis
ayima, בסריס, besaris, or it's a eunuch. Of course, notice what the
גמרא Gemara does not mention as a possibility: maybe you're a man
without a beard. Okay, tells you something culturally that they all had
beards. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara said, yeah, we didn't mean
if you had hair on your face. We meant other parts of
your body, but since there's hair on your face, that would be
a problem. Okay, so anyway, that's how we sort of figured out
this whole issue according to רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. Don't use these
various cleansers that have the possibility of making hair fall off. Now
the גמרא Gemara says, now the גמרא's Gemara going to talk within
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda about which types of cleansers are a problem
or not. We've already mentioned that sand is a potential problem. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, עפר לבינתא שרי. afar levinta shari. Dirt from a stone, from
a brick, that's okay. That will not be so abrasive, which sounds
pretty abrasive to me. So the גאונים Geonim anyway, the גאונים Geonim
say that לבינתא levinta means like לבונה, levona, from frankincense. So that
maybe is less abrasive. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, כוספא דיסמון
שרי. kuspa dyasmon shari. This jasmine, right. So, you know, this type
of a dust, whatever, from the jasmine, that's okay. That will actually
not... רש"י Rashi says it's from sunflowers. But anyway, that's not so
abrasive. For hair. Using it for your hair on שבת, Shabbat, assuming
you rule like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. Okay, that even דבר שאינו
מתכוין... davar she'eino mitkavein... I'm waiting for somebody to ask what about
the סחיטה sechita problem. What about what? Yeah, it says squeeze. What
are you doing on שבת? Shabbat? Yeah, what about squeezing? Right, so
you know, the question about whether they were concerned about squeezing water
from hair is going to be debated later. It's not so clear.
Because the water never, as opposed to squeezing... Like using conditioner. No,
but as opposed to what? It's not really absorbed. Exactly. As opposed
to all the cases of squeezing, the things get absorbed and in
your hair the water just gets between the individual hairs. It doesn't
actually get absorbed, it just gets trapped. So there's a whole discussion
whether squeezing with hair is a problem or not. But it is
interesting that the גמרא Gemara here is discussing basically washing your hair
on שבת Shabbat and the only question it's got is what type
of soap are you using. You had a question? The Hebrew says
sesame pulp. Right, because that's רש"י's, Rashi says it's sesame. Okay, but
I think some of the גאונים Geonim whatever say that it literally
means jasmine, יסמין yasmin is jasmine. But that's רש"י. Rashi. Okay. So
those, so now we're assuming within רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the
whole question is which type of things are not a concern that
they'll pull out the hairs. So we have that, and now we
have a third one. אמר רב פפא אמר רבא, amar Rav Pappa
amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, עפר פלפלי, afar pilpeli, some type
of a dust or some type of a ground pepper. So I,
you know, he's not meaning like black pepper, he means like, you
know, like red pepper. No, no. Red pepper didn't exist then. Oh,
so what did he mean then? It would have to be either
black pepper or white pepper. Really? They didn't have like peppers, like
those things? No, those are new world. Those are new world. Really?
So okay, so using pepper as a cleanser. Alrighty, alright, moving on.
I'd rather have my dirty hair anyway. אמר רב ששת, amar Rav
Sheshet, ברדא שרי, barda shari, which is like, the ברדא barda was
some classic type of a soap, that's allowed. מאי ברדא? mai barda?
What is it? אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, תילתא אהלא, tilta
ahala, a third aloe, ותילתא אסא, vetilta asa, a third myrtle, הדס,
hadas, ותילתא סיגלי, vetilta sigli, and a third of... what's סיגלי sigli
in modern Hebrew? סגול sagol is in purple. No, isn't it סיגלי
sigli in modern Hebrew violet? So look at רש"י. Rashi. So רש"י
Rashi for סיגלי, sigli, רש"י Rashi says: עשב שקורין ויאולו ויש בו
שלושה עלין, esev shekorin viol vyesh bo shlosha alin, so violet. Okay,
so basically the violet and the aloe are non-abrasive. The only concern
here is the... I'm sorry, the violet and the הדס hadas are
considered to be non-abrasive. Only the aloe is potentially the abrasive. So
he said it's a third aloe and therefore it's okay. אמר רב
נחמיה בר יוסף, amar Rav Nechemya bar Yosef, כל היכא דליכא רובא
אהלא, kol heicha deleika ruba ahala, as long as... so he's even
more lenient. So they're using this mixture as a soap? This is
the type of a mixture as a soap. So that's okay. It
sounds like something that's hard, and then doesn't you have other problems
of you know... Oh, that's a good question. Not clear. I mean
I'm saying soap. Who knows? Maybe it's more like a liquid form.
Okay, whether there's actually a problem by soap of ממחק memachek or
whatever we can discuss some other time. Okay, there's a good argument
to say not, but let's bracket it. We tend to not use
it because they say you're smoothing the soap. But the reality is:
Are you really trying to smooth the soap or are you just
trying to get the soap onto your hair? Right, anyway, okay. But
maybe the גמרא's Gemara talking more of a liquid form. I don't
know. It'd be interesting to explore what those realities were. Anyway, but
he says it's a third of this aloe and that's non-abrasive. So
the next opinion is even more lenient. כל היכא דליכא רובא אהלא,
kol heicha deleika ruba ahala, as long as it's not a majority
of aloe, שפיר דמי, shapir dami, okay. But a majority of aloe
is already too abrasive. בעי מיניה רב ששת. bei minei Rav Sheshet.
So asked from רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So anyway, that's the end
of that digression which was fascinating about showering and your hair on
שבת, Shabbat, but it was all because... Because we were discussing the
possibility of sand and is sand מוקצה, muktzah, and sand was one
of the things which might have been a type of soap and
might have been abrasive. Okay, so anyway, but let's just remember where
this came from was a discussion of what do you need to
take something that normally is מוקצה muktzah and change its designation, and
is it enough to intend to do something physical or to use.
Yeah, I think it's not, I think I'm misidentifying it as aloe
because first of all that's aloe is not abrasive. It's a soothing
thing. Yeah. I was wondering about that but the English signs out
there I was going by, he said aloe. Yeah. Oh really? Certain
plants change to holler indigenous to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. One of
them is the crystalline ice plant and there's a picture. Oh, he's
got ice plant. He says ice plant. But does he doesn't say
aloe? Actually it looks like an aloe plant. Referring to aloe as
a genus rather than a... Oh I see, yeah. I was wondering
about that because aloe is not, you know, you know, is not
abrasive. Right. Yeah. Maybe it depends how you process it, but okay
maybe it's not aloe. Whatever it is, this אהלא ahala is I
mean I think even in תנ"ך Tanach you have אהלא ahala as
a cleanser, don't you? אם תכבסי בנתר ובורית. im techabsi b'neter uborit.
You have בורית, borit, you have anyway. Okay, anyway, but anyway that
was definitely the abrasive component of that mixture. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara goes on to a different topic. אמר רב נחמיה בר יוסף
Amar Rav Nechemia bar Yosef כל היכא, kol heicha, we learned this
yesterday. בעי מיניה רב ששת. Baie minei Rav Sheshet. He asked the
following question from רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. מהו לפצוע זיתים בשבת? Mahu
lifzo'ach zeitim b'Shabbos? Can you, can you smoosh, no not pick, smoosh
olives on like a hard surface, a rock on שבת? Shabbos? Now
why are you doing this? Either you're trying to get out, you
know, maybe you want to, רש"י Rashi says you want to make
the olives somehow tastier, this I don't know but somehow do it.
Okay, we're going to see in a minute that something is going
to waste. So according to רש"י Rashi what's going to waste is
that you are the oil is going to waste but you're making
the olives taste better. Another thing might be that you actually want
the oil out of it and then that ties into the connection
here because they would use the oil as a type of a
cleanser or something to wash their hands with. Otherwise, what is this
discussion doing here? Right? That's תוספות's Tosafot argument there is that you
want the oil from it and therefore you act it on שבת
Shabbos which is funny, shouldn't that be the normal prohibition of squeezing
fruits to get their juices? Anyway, that's what the question was. One
minute. Right. Or no, I'm sorry, so maybe for תוספות Tosafot maybe
you're not actually washing your hands with the oil, maybe you're washing
your hands with the smooshed olive because if you are actually trying
to extract the oil it wouldn't make any sense why there would
even be a suggestion it would be allowed. So according to רש"י
Rashi you're smooshing the olives to make it taste better, it has
nothing to do with the conversation with what we've been talking about.
According to תוספות Tosafot you're smooshing the olives to use it to
like rub on your hands. Okay, but either way the oil is
going to waste and there's a question as well about maybe you're
making something like fixing food and that becomes another interesting question. Is
there a problem of תיקון אוכלין? tikun ochlin? Of making food fixing
it and making it edible without actually doing בישול bishul and without
actually doing something that falls into one of the other categories of
מלאכה? melacha? So that was the question for רש"י, Rashi, right? Here
you are, you're basically making it more edible through smooshing it, is
that okay? תוספות Tosafot says can you smoosh it in order to
use it on your hands, so it's presumably edible otherwise but anyway
can you smoosh it to use it on your hands? So let's
see. And the oil is going to waste. The oil is going
to waste. And you couldn't get the oil if you wanted to?
I don't know, I don't know. Let's read what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that was
the question. אמר להו Amar lehu וכי בחול מי הותר? v'chi b'chol
mi hutra? So what do you ask me about שבת? Shabbos? Whoever
said you could do it during the weekday? Now why can't you
do something during the weekday? So this is how he's answering the
answer because you're wasting the oil. Okay, and therefore whoever said you're
allowed to do it in the weekday? קסבר Kasavar he assumes משום
הפסד אוכלין mishum hefsed ochlin that he doesn't like you to do
this stuff even though you'd say I'm making the olive taste better,
but you're wasting the oil. לימא, Leima, which is funny because, you
know, you'd think that you can choose which parts to use or
not use and if you're making one part better, but let's take
a look. פליגי, Pligi, לימא פליגי דשמואל? Leima pligi d'Shmuel? Maybe this
argues on שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל D'amar Shmuel עושה אדם כל צרכו
בפת. oseh adam kol tzarcho b'pat. You can use bread for anything.
You can use bread to wipe up your gravy, to wipe up
a sponge because basically and it's not considered that you're misusing food.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמי בפת לא מאיסא. Ami b'pat
lo me'isa. The bread if you use it for something else doesn't
become disgusting and it will still be edible afterwards. הני מאיסי. Hani
me'isi. This is disgusting or at least again the oil part is
no longer edible and maybe it should not be allowed to waste
food even if it's for the sake of, you know, doing something
purposeful. So אמימר ומר זוטרא ורב אשי, Amemar uMar Zutra v'Rav Ashi,
so we don't have an answer to that. Okay, so now אמימר
ומר זוטרא ורב אשי הוו יתבי, Amemar uMar Zutra v'Rav Ashi hava
yatvi, איתי לקמייהו Aiti l'kamaiehu ברדא. barda. Now we're back right back
to the to the ברדא, barda, which is this cleanser. So you
see it's bizarre that we have this discussion of olives in the
middle of this discussion of cleansers, which is why תוספות Tosafot was
saying that you're using the smooshed olive as a type of a
cleanser. So now these three were sitting and they brought in front
of them this ברדא, barda, this cleanser and presumably it was שבת.
Shabbos. אמימר ורב אשי משו. Amemar v'Rav Ashi mashu. So אמימר Amemar
and רב אשי Rav Ashi used it, washed their hands and face
and Maybe even their hands, מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* did not wash
himself with it. אמרו ליה *Amru lei*, they said to him, לא
lo, סבר ליה מר להא דאמר רב ששת ברדא שרי *Lo savar
lei Mar la-ha-de-amar Rav Sheshet Barda sharei*, don't you hold of what
רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* said that ברדא *Barda*'s allowed? It's not a
problem about hair falling out? רב מרדכי *Rav Mordechai* said back to
them, he answered for מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra*. מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra*
didn't even respond, so רב מרדכי *Rav Mordechai* said, בר מיני דמר
*Bar minei de-Mar*, no, forget about you know it don't forget about
what he says, דאפילו בחול נמי לא סבירא ליה *De-afillu be-chol nami
lo sevira lei*. So he doesn't even like to use the sand.
Found it before like you know that sand was perhaps more acceptable,
but it's funny, sand wasn't acceptable for רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, so
but anyway but he says you know don't worry about him, he
doesn't use he doesn't like using cleansers on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* at
all. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says... oh we meant חול *chol*
as in sand and not as in חול *chol* meaning use it
during the week. Oh I'm sorry, you're right. You're right. One minute.
One minute. One minute. Yeah I'm sorry you're right you're right. I
was confused. I'm sorry. You're right because it wouldn't make sense. Sand
is more problematic. And anyway the continuing גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes it
clear. Thank you very much. It actually does pick up exactly the
theme before about the olives. Why are you giving me a hard
point about שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* or what's the point of שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbat*, even in the weekdays it's not allowed. Thank you very much.
Yeah I got confused. So says like this. אמרו ליה *Amru lei*
רב מרדכי *Rav Mordechai* בר מיני דמר *Bar minei de-Mar*. Don't worry
מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* about that. דאפילו בחול נמי לא סבירא ליה
*De-afillu be-chol nami lo sevira lei*. Even on the weekday he doesn't
use these cleansers. Why not? סבר לה *Savar lah* כי הא דתניא
*ki ha de-tanya* like we done in a ברייתא *Beraita*, מגרר אדם
גלידי צואה וגלידי מכה שעל בשרו *Magar adam glidei tzoa ve-glidei maka
she-al besaro*. You can scrape away like excrement from your skin you
know that got on it. Yeah it was a lovely very clean
society then. Okay and other types of scabs. בשביל צערו *Bishvil tzaaro*
if they're painful to you or you just don't like them being
on your skin. אבל אם בשביל ליפו *Aval im bishvil l'yafo* but
don't scrape your skin in order to look nice, אסור *Assur*. That's
forbidden. Why? Because again this now gets back to Michael's point it's
a type of a בגד אשה *beged isha*, right? So the idea
that they used to scrape their skin so it would look red,
ruddy and you know and whatever and look nice and soft or
whatever you're not allowed to do that that's a type of a
בגד אשה *beged isha*. Okay so don't do it. So he felt
using any cleanser, so I'm going to be very מחמיר *machmir* on
בגד אשה *beged isha* and I'm not going to use any cleanser
at all. No soap at all. So that's what he says. So
he wouldn't even do it during the weekday. All right so don't
worry it's not a שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* issue. It's a weekday issue.
ואינהו כמאן סברו *Ve-inhu ke-man savru*? Who do they hold like? כי
הא דתניא *Ki ha de-tanya* like we done in a ברייתא *Beraita*,
רוחץ אדם פניו ידיו ורגליו בכל יום בשביל קונו *Rocheitz adam panav
yadav ve-raglav be-chol yom bishvil kono*. No they felt no that you're
supposed to actually keep clean. Cleanliness is close to godliness. You're supposed
to bathe every day in order for the honor of your Maker,
of your Creator, משום שנאמר *bishum she-ne'emar* כל פעל ה' למענהו *kol
poal Hashem le-maanehu*. Everything God made is for God's glory. Human beings
are made בצלם אלקים *betzelem Elokim* in the image of God and
therefore keeping your body clean shows respect for God and therefore there's
an idea of cleanliness. פניו ידיו ורגליו *Panav yadav ve-raglav* at least.
Right well that you know that was the minimum we could have
been. It actually anyway so that's quite fascinating so he was מחמיר
*machmir* to just do basic issues of hygiene because it was too
much like בגד אשה *beged isha*. Okay but anyway but right Michael's
right actually the point was it was parallel the גמרא *Gemara* before
about the olives which is you're telling me whether I can do
it on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, so I'm saying I can't even do
it during the weekday, one had to do for these other various
reasons. Okay so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues with back to מוקצה
muktzah *muktzeh* issues. So now you've got your pot, this insulator, these
sheep shearings around your pot in a box. It's מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh*,
how do you get to your pot? One is you just lift
up the lid it falls off. Then the question is can you
remove the pot or are you afraid that the sheep shearings will
come and fill up the hole and then that will create a
problem. So let's take a look that was debated in the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah*. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Eliezer ben Azariah אומר קופה
מטה על צדה *Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer kuppa matti al tzidah*,
you can pour the whole box out ונוטל *ve-notel* and take it,
but you cannot remove the pot and put it back because then
the hole will get filled up. Now what is the problem by
the way about the hole getting filled up before we read the
גמרא *Gemara*? רש"י *Rashi* says the problem is is that it's מוקצה
muktzah *muktzeh*. The hole gets filled up with these shearings. You're going
to want to make space for the hole. So maybe you'll move
it away with your hands the shearings. Maybe you'll use the pot
to move it away. That's no longer טלטול מן הצד *tiltul min
ha-tzad*. There you're basically trying to move the shearings to make space
for the pot. You're not just worried about moving the pot. You're
trying to move the shearings. It's a מוקצה *muktzeh* problem. That's what
רש"י *Rashi* says. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says another read which is we're
going to read very soon that while you're allowed to insulate before
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* and you're allowed to take it and return it
because then it's like continuing an existing status, what you're not allowed
to do is insulate on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. Even in something that
just preserves the heat. ערב שבת Erev Shabbos *Erev Shabbat* you can
insulate in something that preserves the heat. On שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* you
cannot anew insulate in something. I cannot take my pot that I've
not insulated at all שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* morning and wrap it in
towels, okay, to preserve the heat. Okay? So, get it? ערב שבת
it cannot be in something that adds the heat, on שבת it
cannot be in something that preserves the heat. So, what do you
do? You did it ערב שבת in something that preserves the heat.
Now you took it off on שבת, you took out the pot.
Now you're allowed to put it back. It's not considered like a
new insulating, it's continuing the old status. So תוספות asks, ah, but
if the hole fills up and now you have to make the
hole anew, now it's like a new act of insulating and you're
not allowed to do that on שבת. So two ways of understanding
what is the problem with the hole filling up. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. So therefore רבי אלעזר Rebbi Eliezer says pour
it out so you don't have to worry about it, and the
rabbis aren't concerned. ואמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי, Ve'amar
Rebbi Abba amar Rebbi Chiya bar Ashi, or אמר רב, amar Rav,
maybe not, הכל מודים, Hakol modim, everybody agrees, שנתקלקלה הגומא שאסור להחזיר,
shenitkalkela haguma she'asur lehachzir, that if the hole did get filled up
and got ruined that you can't put it back. תנן, Tenan, now
let's look at a little of our משנה. Mishnah. חכמים אומרים נוטלו
ומחזירו, Chachamim omrim notlo umachziro, you take it and return it. So
היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דלא נתקלקלה הגומא, ee
delo nitkalkela haguma, if the hole was still in good shape, שפיר
קאמרי רבנן, shapir kaamri rabanan, so they have a good position. What's
the reason of that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה doesn't allow you to
put it back? אלא לאו, ela lav, it must be אף על
פי שנתקלקלה הגומא, af al pi shenitkalkela haguma, that the hole did
get filled up and nevertheless the rabbis allowed you to return it.
So basically it seems like the debate is can you put the
pot back after the hole filled up. That seems to be the
debate, not like he said. The גמרא says לא, ולעולם דלא נתקלקלה,
ve'le'olam delo nitkalkela, the hole did not get filled. והכא בחששין קמיפלגי,
vehacha be'chosheshin kamiflegi, the debate is whether you have to be concerned
that that might happen. מר סבר חוששין, mar savar chosheshin, one says
you are concerned, שמא תתקלקל הגומא, shema tiskalkel haguma, that it'll get
ruined, ומר סבר אין חוששין, umar savar ein chosheshin, you're not concerned.
So this is a very stringent way of reading the משנה. Mishnah
The one way to read the משנה Mishnah is that the rabbis
don't care if the hole gets filled up. So, make the hole
anew. It's not a מוקצה problem, it's not a הטמנה hatmana problem,
make the hole anew. He says, no, that's not what's happening. If
the hole got filled up, everybody says it's a problem. The debate
is whether we allow you to take it out out of a
concern that the hole might get filled up and still put it
back. Yeah, but then I guess the concern is that, no, you're
going to want to keep your food hot and you're not going
to put it back regardless. Okay, so let's just read a little
bit more. אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, האי סליקוסטא, דעצה שלפא
והדר דעצה, hai slikusta de'atza shalfa vehadar de'atza, this סליקוסטא slikusta which
basically רש״י Rashi says is like a type of a nice type
of a fragrant plant that they would bring to people to important
people, they have it in a pot to smell. It wouldn't be
growing but apparently they would keep it sort of stuck into dirt.
A plant. A plant, right. So the question is going to be
are we concerned that you'll bring it to the person on שבת
to pluck it out, it's not a problem of growing and of
קוצר kotzer because it's like it's already been cut. They'll pluck it
out, they'll smell it, and they'll put it back into the dirt,
and that's a problem of making a hole in the dirt, which
רש״י Rashi is just a מוקצה issue again. Okay, so that's the
question, but it's obviously analogous to this making this hole in this
insulator. האי סליקוסטא hai slikusta, דעצה שלפא והדר דעצה, de'atza shalfa vehadar
de'atza, if you put it in, pulled it out, and put it
in again before שבת, שריא, sharya, then it's okay, the hole is
big enough and we're not afraid that you'll make a new, like
you'll move stuff in when you're putting it in on שבת. ואי
לא אסיר, ve'ee lo assir, and if it's not, it's forbidden. Similarly,
אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, האי סכינא דביני אורבי, hai sakina de'beini ourbi,
they would keep knives between the bricks, like in a hole in
their brick wall. דעצה שלפא והדר דעצה שריא, de'atza shalfa vehadar de'atza
sharya, if you put it in the wall, made the hole, removed
it and put it back in, then you're okay, then we're not
afraid when you take it out on שבת and put it back
in you'll make a bigger hole. ואי לא אסיר, ve'ee lo assir,
and if it's not, it's forbidden. And we will pick up with
this tomorrow. Again, it's not clear that the issue is necessarily just
a מוקצה issue, which is the way רש״י Rashi wants to read
it. You know, maybe it's a type of a בנין binyan issue,
you're making a hole in a wall and now you're making it
as a better place to store knives, so maybe it's like a
בנין binyan problem. Okay? So it's a little unclear what in each
case what exactly the problem is, but the thing that connects them
is that you don't want to be making the hole anew or
making the hole bigger on שבת and in that way connects to
the case of our משנה and therefore you have to make it
like
big enough before שבת and we will continue to see cases like
this tomorrow.